<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Khris Griffis, Ph.D.</title>
    <description>Neurophysiology | Statistics | Biosignals Analysis | Data Science</description>
    <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://khrisgriffis.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 16:38:44 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 16:38:44 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investigation of the functional impact of CHED- and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0296928&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mutations in the solute linked carrier family 4 member 11 (SLC4A11) gene are associated with congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED) and Fuchs corneal endothelial dystrophy type 4 (FECD4), both characterized by corneal endothelial cell (CEnC) dysfunction and/or cell loss leading to corneal edema and visual impairment. In this study, we characterize the impact of CHED-/FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations on CEnC function and SLC4A11 protein localization by generating and comparing human CEnC (hCEnC) lines expressing wild type SLC4A11 ((\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;em&gt;{WT})) or mutant SLC4A11 harboring CHED-/FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations ((\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;/em&gt;{MU})). (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;em&gt;{WT}) and (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;/em&gt;{MU}) hCEnC lines were generated to express either SLC4A11 variant 2 ((V2&lt;em&gt;{WT}) and (V2&lt;/em&gt;{MU})) or variant 3 ((V3&lt;em&gt;{WT}) and (V3&lt;/em&gt;{MU})), the two major variants expressed in ex vivo hCEnC. Functional assays were performed to assess cell barrier, proliferation, viability, migration, and (NH_3)-induced membrane conductance. We demonstrate (\mathrm{SLC4A11}^{-/-}) and (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;em&gt;{MU}) hCEnC lines exhibited increased migration rates, altered proliferation and decreased cell viability compared to (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;/em&gt;{WT}) hCEnC. Additionally, (\mathrm{SLC4A11}^{-/-}) hCEnC demonstrated decreased cell-substrate adhesion and membrane capacitances compared to (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;em&gt;{WT}) hCEnC. Induction with 10mM (NH_4Cl) led (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;/em&gt;{WT}) hCEnC to depolarize; conversely, (\mathrm{SLC4A11}^{-/-}) hCEnC hyperpolarized and the majority of (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;em&gt;{MU}) hCEnC either hyperpolarized or had minimal membrane potential changes following (NH_4Cl) induction. Immunostaining of primary hCEnC and (\mathrm{SLC4A11}&lt;/em&gt;{WT}) hCEnC lines for SLC4A11 demonstrated predominately plasma membrane staining with poor or partial colocalization with mitochondrial marker COX4 within a subset of punctate subcellular structures. Overall, our findings suggest CHED-associated SLC4A11 mutations likely lead to hCEnC dysfunction, and ultimately CHED, by interfering with cell migration, proliferation, viability, membrane conductance, barrier function, and/or cell surface localization of the SLC4A11 protein in hCEnC. Additionally, based on their similar subcellular localization and exhibiting similar cell functional profiles, protein isoforms encoded by SLC4A11 variant 2 and variant 3 likely have highly overlapping functional roles in hCEnC.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:01:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/Chung2024.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/Chung2024.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Adjunct Faculty - Depts. Mechanical Engineering &amp; Kinesiology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course Design and Instruction&lt;/strong&gt;
Experimental Methods (Mechanical Engineering): Redesigned and taught a course on probability, statistics, and measurement uncertainty, aligning lab components with modern experimental methods across engineering disciplines. Delivered 2-hour weekly lectures and supervised 4 lab sections, each 2.3 hours per week, teaching over 50 students per semester.
Neuroplasticity and Disease (Kinesiology): Developed and instructed a course on neuromuscular disorders and neuroplasticity, focusing on physiological mechanisms and their pathological implications. Conducted 3-hour weekly lectures, teaching over 75 students per semester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interdisciplinary Research and Collaboration&lt;/strong&gt;
Led collaborative research initiatives in the field of Spinal Plasticity and Spinal Cord Injury. Fostered partnerships with academic institutions for joint research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Student Mentorship and Management&lt;/strong&gt;
Mentored and managed a graduate student assistant, supporting their development and coordinating their contributions to course activities. Provided guidance and support to over 125 students each semester, promoting academic and professional growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curriculum Development&lt;/strong&gt;
Contributed to enhancing departmental curricula, promoting interdisciplinary learning and ensuring alignment with industry standards.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/adjunct.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/adjunct.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Essentially Me</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;essentially-me&quot;&gt;Essentially Me&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;!-- Einstein quote --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many times a day I realize how much my own outer and inner life is built upon the labors of my fellow men, both living and dead, and how earnestly I must exert myself in order to give in return as much as I have received.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#Einstein1930&quot;&gt;Einstein, 1930&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- welcome --&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Hello, I’m so glad you found this page. My name is Khris. The day of this writing is Apr 20, 2023, and it’s my 39&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; birthday. I have decided to start this professional site to host ideas and projects that I work on. I have a number of posts in the works that are based on some of my doctoral work. Oh, I have a Ph.D. from the University of California, Los Angles, in the field of Molecular, Cellular, and Integrative Physiology. My area of expertise is in visual neuroscience. My &lt;a href=&quot;../publications/griffis2022b.html&quot;&gt;doctoral work&lt;/a&gt; investigated molecular mechanisms of photon detection and processing in the mammalian rod visual pathway (&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#griffis2022mechanisms&quot;&gt;Griffis, 2022&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;As a vision scientist, I gained skills and experience that opened my understanding of the world, made me a critical thinker, an experimentalist, a leader, an observer, a listener, and a lecturer. I was able to utilize my passions to discover new insights into how our eyes capture the world. I gained experience in technical fields such as statistics, machine learning, data science, dynamical modeling, computer science, electrical engineering, robotics, optics, lasers, and remote sensing. These topics were in addition to the core of my physiological study, which focused heavily on all of neuroscience, from dissections and live imaging to spike sorting and modeling. I also have a wealth of hands-on experience in the wet lab from working with biologically hazardous agents to immuno-chemistry and cell culture. I’ve picked up quite a few tools over the decades, and I’m not done yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;I am always eager to learn, to educate, to explore the universe, to collaborate, to investigate a thing from every conceivable angle, and to think deeply (sometimes about nothing at all). My most favorite time is spent with my family, outside somewhere, where my two young boys can explore, ask questions, and seek out answers (even if just dreaming up an answer). I’m using this site as a professional bookshelf, but that doesn’t mean there won’t be stories about my personal life. I hope you will check back and see if any of the posts I make in the future make any impact on your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khris&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- personal statement-ish --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-scientific-journey&quot;&gt;My Scientific Journey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Following my undergraduate degree in Physiological Science (UCLA), I joined the field of neurodegenerative repair, focusing on spinal-cord injury research in the lab of Patricia E. Phelps at UCLA. Beginning in 2011, I focused primarily on the potential benefit of olfactory ensheathing cells (OECs) as an &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; model of spinal cord injury, and I collaborated on 3 projects assessing the therapeutic effects of OEC engraftments on neural regeneration. In 2013, I began the Master of Science degree in the Department of Integrative Biology and Physiology at UCLA and was able to continue my work in neural repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Throughout my tenure in the Phelps lab, I had the opportunity to familiarize myself with several biological tools, including bench work from PCR, western-blot, and immunohistochemistry to cell imaging, cell culture, histology, and cryostat slicing. I managed upwards of 4 rodent colonies as the principle lead of animal husbandry, where I selectively maintained the colonies based on a desired level of expression of transgenic DNA, which I assessed by biochemical methods, e.g., by PCR. I worked closely with the UCLA Department of Laboratory Animal Medicine as the first line of vetinary needs for these colonies. Employing my love for statistics, and my hobby of computer science&lt;a href=&quot;#fn_1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I developed novel analysis methods with Python, R, and MATLAB, to assess the extent of neural circuitry regeneration after spinal transection from electromyographical, transcranial, and spinal epidural electrical recordings. I took advantage of the opportunity to deepen my understanding of electronic circuits, and how they parallel with biological signals, by working with post-doctoral researchers in Dr. Reggie Edgerton’s lab at UCLA and our collaborators at CalTech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;When I began spinal-cord research, I was most interested in neural connections and the complex circuitry they form. I decided that no biological system is better suited to ask questions of this nature than vision, specifically, the retina. To my great fortune, right there at UCLA was a world renowned photoreceptor physiologist, Dr. Gordon Fain, and his highly successful and brilliant disciple, Dr. Alapakkam “Sam” Sampath. I sought to join Dr. Sampath’s lab with success and I began my Ph.D. journey in the Spring of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;The Sampath lab was an environment comprised of experienced students, post-doctoral researchers, and a wealth of collaborators across the globe, and I quickly became a part of the team. At the time I joined the lab, Sam had recently moved from the Keck School of Medicine (USC) to UCLA and, albeit functional for experiments, the lab was in the process of upgrading our physiology rigs and waiting for the Jules Stein Eye Institute to finish remodeling so the lab could move to its final location. I was able to use my hardware and software experience to upgrade the existing acquisition systems and to build new light stimulus pathways. In 2017, the lab moved to the Jules Stein building and I was fortunate enough to build my own rig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Over my tenure in the Sampath lab, I developed novel methods for analyzing time-series, electrophysiological data. I contributed to mathematical modeling of photoreceptor light responses, where I leveraged the power of resampling statistics for model selection, uncertainty quantification and parameter estimation. I contributed to an open source software acquisition system and wrote a MATLAB-based application to visualize and analyze electrophysiological data offline. Aside from the technical work, I contributed to 8 collaborations, from which 4 separate NIH grants were awarded, 4 manuscripts were published (1 more in preparation as of Apr 20, 2023), and several conference proceedings were published (&lt;em&gt;for example:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#chung2022investigation&quot;&gt;Chung &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt;, 2022; Kim &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt;, 2018&lt;/a&gt;). Below, I’ve detailed my contributions to science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- contributios to science --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scientific-contributions-to-date&quot;&gt;Scientific Contributions (to date)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;During my time in the laboratory of Patricia E. Phelps, I focused primarily on investigating the therapeutic potential of OECs in regenerating functional circuits following complete spinal cord injury. As a consequence of my technical background and my multiple roles within the lab, I was able to contribute to several projects with collaborators. During my tenure in the lab of Alapakkam Sampath, I was fortunate to leverage my technical background and my passion for math and statistics to contribute novel research and expand understanding of light detection and processing in the retina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A major contributing factor to any cellular transplant therapy is that of cell survival. By using intrinsic labeling in commercially available, eGFP transgenic Sprague Dawley rats, I assisted in generating OEC primary cultures that we transplanted into age-matched female Sprague Dawley rats which had received spinal cord injury. Using immunohistochemical and stereological methods, I quantified the amount of surviving control fibroblasts or OECs 1, 2, and 4 weeks post-injury and assessed the extent of serotonergic (5-HT) axon die back. I also organized and assisted in the surgical implantation of transcranial stimulation electrodes, electromyographic recording electrodes, and cellular implants. Using transcranial stimulation to evoke descending potentials and assess potential regenerated connectivity, I helped evaluate rats at 2 and 7 months after injury. We found that training, spinal cord stimulation, and OEC treatment yielded moderate functional recovery in spinal transected rats.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;R. R. Khankan, &lt;em&gt;K. G. Griffis&lt;/em&gt;, I. B. Wanner, H. Zhong, R. R. Roy, V. R. Edgerton, P. E. Phelps. Survival and migration of adult rat eGFP-OECs after a complete spinal cord transection. Program No. 466.02. 2013 Neuroscience Meeting Planner. San Diego, CA: Society for Neuroscience, 2013. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A. K. Yeung, G. Garcia-Alias, &lt;em&gt;K. G. Griffis&lt;/em&gt;, R. R. Khankan, H. Zhong, *R. R. Roy, P. E. Phelps, V. Edgerton. Spinal cord epidural stimulation and climb training enhance axon regeneration in rats transplanted with olfactory ensheathing cells after a complete spinal cord transection. Neuroscience 2015 Abstracts. Chicago, IL: Society for Neuroscience, 2015. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Following the cell viability experiments, I hypothesized that transplanted OECs affected glial scar formation in a potentially beneficial way. Using immunohistochemistry and confocal microscopy, I evaluated astrocyte morphology around the lesion, as well as the presence of activated microglia and invading macrophages. We showed that, compared to control fibroblast treated rats, the acute immune response and the deposition of CS-56+ proteins were markedly reduced in OEC treated rats at all acute time points following injury. We determined that OECs reduce lesion size in early acute responses, but by 8 weeks these effects, along with the OECs, are diminished. Further, 5-HT+ axons were more abundant in OEC treated rats, implying that OECs modulate the immune response to facilitate axonal regeneration. The evolution of this project produced two abstracts and two manuscripts in 2016 and 2018.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thornton, M. A., Mehta, M. D., Morad, T. T., Ingraham, K. L., Khankan, R. R., Griffis, K. G., Yeung, A. K., Zhong, H., Roy, R. R., Edgerton, V. R., &amp;amp; Phelps, P. E. (2018). Evidence of axon connectivity across a spinal cord transection in rats treated with epidural stimulation and motor training combined with olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation. Experimental Neurology, 309, 119–133. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.EXPNEUROL.2018.07.015&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Khankan, R. R., Griffis, K. G., Haggerty-Skeans, J. R., Zhong, H., Roy, R. R., Reggie Edgerton, V., &amp;amp; Phelps, P. E. (2016). Olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation after a complete spinal cord transection mediates neuroprotective and immunomodulatory mechanisms to facilitate regeneration. Journal of Neuroscience, 36(23). https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0085-16.2016&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Khankan, R.R., Ingraham, K.L., Haggerty-Skeans, J.R., Griffis, K.G., Zhong, H., Roy,R., Edgerton, V.R., Phelps, P.E. Olfactory ensheathing cells reduce inhibitory factors at the astroglial scar-border after a complete mid-thoracic spinal cord transection. Program No. 338.07/V24 Neuroscience 2015 Abstracts. Chicago, IL: Society for Neuroscience, 2015. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;R. R. Khankan, K. G. Griffis, D. N. Perez, J. R. Haggerty-Skeans, H. Zhong, R. R. Roy, V. R. Edgerton, *P. E. Phelps. Olfactory ensheathing cells and fibroblasts differ their modification of the lesion site after complete spinal cord transection. Program No. 422.26. 2014 Neuroscience Meeting Planner. Washington, DC: Society for Neuroscience, 2014. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I became interested in cellular physiology and had the opportunity to use both my cell-culture experience and statistical knowledge to assist a colleague in studying the role of calcium oscillations in a module of acute lung injury of human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells (hPASMCs). To study possible mechanisms, we investigated effects of IL-1b on calcium flux in hPASMCs in response to vasoconstrictor endothelin-1. I developed an analysis method, using machine learning and other statistical methods, to identify oscillating and non-oscillating responders. We showed that IL-1b is strongly associated with increases in oscillating responders. Follow-up work from this project is ongoing, and a manuscript is in preparation.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elizabeth H. Kim, Khris G. Griffis, Meredith Sheppard, Suliman Alamro, Daniel Tabari, Alan Garfinkel, and Heather D. Jones. Calcium Oscillations in Human Pulmonary Artery Smooth Muscle Cells: Developing a Hierarchical Clustering Method for Analysis and the Effects of IL-1b. The FASEB Journal 2018 32:1_supplement, 628.1-628.1&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a collaboration between the laboratories of Alapakkam Sampath and Anthony J. Aldave, I did whole-cell patch recordings on isolated mouse corneal endothelial cells in culture to study the functional role of SLC4A11 in a murine model of congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED). SCL4A11 is essential for facilitating energy producing glutaminolysis, maintaining antioxidant signaling, and preventing apoptosis in corneal endothelial cells. We showed that reduced steady-state ATP levels and subsequent activation of the AMPK-p53 pathway provide a link between the metabolic functional deficit and transcriptome alterations. We also found evidence that insufficient ATP to maintain the Na+/K+-ATPase corneal endothelial pump is the cause of the edema that characterizes SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Zhang, W., Frausto, R., Chung, D.D., Griffis, C.G., Kao, L., Chen, A., Azimov, R., Sampath, A.P., Kurtz, I., Aldave, A.J.   (2020)  Energy shortage in human and mouse models of SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies .  Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science,  61(8),  39.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chung, D., Chen, A., Choo, C., Zhang, W., Griffis, C., Bonezzi, P., Sampath, A.P., Aldave, A.J.   (2022)  Investigation of the functional impact of CHED- and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells .  Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science,  63(7),  3624-A0189.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I provided patch-clamp recordings from rod photoreceptors and statistical analysis to a model of mouse cone photoreceptors developed by Jürgen Reingruber and Gordon Fain. I helped to show that the kinetic changes that transform the rod response into that of the cone are characterized by these three key parameters: 1) reduction in transduction amplification, 2) increased dark turnover rate of cGMP, and 3) increased decay rate of activated phosphodiesterase.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reingruber, J., N.T. Ingram, Griffis, K.G., and G.L. Fain. 2020. A kinetic analysis of mouse rod and cone photoreceptor responses. Journal of Physiology, in press.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending from the collaboration in which I used information theoretic clustering of calcium oscillations in hPASMCs, I collaborated with Alan Garfinkel and Christopher Colwell to study oscillations in the core body temperature (CBT) of mice with a genetic perturbation (Q175) that mimics Huntington’s disease (HD) in humans. Circadian rhythms in CBT have been widely studied, but fewer studies have explored higher-frequency (ultradian) rhythms in detail. We analyzed CBT recordings from young and middle-aged wild-type mice as well as from the Q175 model of HD, at sufficient temporal resolution to address the question of ultradian rhythms. We used model selection methods to show that the overall circadian pattern was better fit by a square wave than a sine wave. Then, using Fourier analysis of the CBT rhythms, we identified the spectral signature of an 8-hour oscillation that occurs in the night but not the day, an observation that can be confirmed by direct inspection of the rhythms. This diurnal amplitude modulation of the 8-hour rhythm was lost with aging as well as in the HD model. Thus, the impact of aging and disease is seen here in the loss of the ability to separate rhythms into a daytime phase and a nighttime phase. These findings raise the possibility that ultradian rhythms in CBT may be a useful biomarker for the pathology within the central nervous system.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;griffis2022circadian&quot;&gt;Griffis, C.G., Mistry, J., Islam, K., Cutler, T., Colwell, C.S., &amp;amp; Garfinkel, A. (2022) Circadian and ultradian rhythms in normal mice and in a mouse model of Huntington’s disease. &lt;i&gt;Chronobiology International&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;b&gt;39&lt;/b&gt;, 513–524.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light adaptation adjusts the sensitivity of vision as ambient illumination changes. Adaptation for scotopic (rod) vision is known to occur partly in the rods and partly in the rest of the retina from presynaptic and postsynaptic mechanisms. We recorded light responses of rods and rod bipolar cells to identify different components of adaptation and study their mechanisms. We show that bipolar-cell sensitivity largely follows adaptation of the rods, but that light too dim to adapt the rods produces a linearization of the bipolar-cell response dynamics and a surprising decrease in maximum response amplitude, both mediated by a change in intracellular Ca2+. These findings provide a new understanding of how the retina responds to changes in ambient illumination.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Khris G. Griffis, Katherine E. Fehlhaber, Fred Rieke, and Alapakkam P. Sampath. (2023). Light adaptation of retinal rod bipolar cells. &lt;em&gt;Submitted to J. Neurosci., pending acceptance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Griffis, C., Sampath, A.P.. (2021)  Rod bipolar cell contributions to changes in response sensitivity during light adaptation .  Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science,  62(8),  2004.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In collaboration with Johan Pahlberg, Ph.D. (NIH/NIDCR), I dissected contributions of transduction-cascade proteins to the continuous noise that obscures the single-photon response in rod photoreceptors and pinpointed the molecular origin of discrete noise, which is indistinguishable from the single-photon response, albeit in the absence of light. To do so, we used novel murine models with graded reductions of G-alpha transducin-1 and PDE-6 levels, and made whole-cell patch recordings in individual rods. Through my experiments, I characterized rod continuous noise and investigated its molecular origin to ask if any one component both sets the continuous noise level and limits the detection of single photons.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Christopher G. Griffis*, Ulisse Bocchero*, Alapakkam P. Sampath and Johan Pahlberg. Origins of discrete and continuous dark noise in rod photoreceptors. &lt;em&gt;In preparation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;fn_1&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:0.7em;&quot;&gt;1: I was that kid in high school who hacked the brand new windows 98 classroom so the teacher couldn&apos;t see I was playing solitaire instead of practicing typing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;chung2022investigation&quot;&gt;Chung, D., Chen, A., Choo, C., Zhang, W., Griffis, C., Bonezzi, P., Sampath, A.P., &amp;amp; Aldave, A.J. (2022) Investigation of the functional impact of CHED-and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells. In &lt;i&gt;Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science&lt;/i&gt;. The Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology, pp. 3624–A0189.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Einstein1930&quot;&gt;Einstein, A. (1930) What I Believe: Living Philosophies XIII. &lt;i&gt;Forum and Century&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;b&gt;LXXXIV&lt;/b&gt;, 192.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;griffis2022mechanisms&quot;&gt;Griffis, C.G. (2022) Mechanisms of Detection Sensitivity and Adaptation in the Rod Visual Pathway (PhD thesis).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kim2018calcium&quot;&gt;Kim, E.H., Griffis, K.G., Sheppard, M., Alamro, S., Tabari, D., Garfinkel, A., &amp;amp; Jones, H.D. (2018) Calcium Oscillations in Human Pulmonary Artery Smooth Muscle Cells: Developing a Hierarchical Clustering Method for Analysis and the Effects of IL-1b. In &lt;i&gt;The FASEB Journal&lt;/i&gt;. Wiley Online Library, pp. 628–621.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/missives/EssentiallyMe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/missives/EssentiallyMe.html</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>missives</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Co-Founder Chief Scientific Officer</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spearheading the development of scientific infrastructure, driving research initiatives, and integrating cutting-edge algorithms into SeqAnalytics’ proprietary RNA sequencing pipeline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delivering high-impact results and managing research consulting services for gene sequencing clients, ensuring top-tier project outcomes and customer satisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shaping the strategic scientific direction of SeqAnalytics’ consulting services, fostering collaborations and joint ventures with leading academic institutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Leading funding acquisition efforts and effectively communicating complex scientific concepts to stakeholders and clients, ensuring alignment and support for SeqAnalytics’ innovative projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/co.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/co.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investigation of the functional impact of CHED- and FECD4-associated  SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iovs.arvojournals.org/article.aspx?articleid=2781541&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To characterize the impact of SLC4A11 mutations associated with congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED) and Fuchs endothelial corneal dystrophy type 4 (FECD4) on corneal endothelial cell (CEnC) function and SLC4A11 protein localization.    Human SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC lines were generated by CRISPR-Cas9 mediated gene editing. SLC4A11 wildtype (SLC4A11WT) and SLC4A11 mutant (SLC4A11MU) human CEnC lines were generated by stable transduction with lentiviruses containing either SLC4A11WT or SLC4A11MU expression vectors harboring CHED-/FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations (CHED: c.374G&amp;gt;A, c.1813C&amp;gt;T, c.2263C&amp;gt;T; FECD4: c.2224G&amp;gt;A). Functional assays were performed to assess cell migration, proliferation, viability after induced oxidative stress and NH4Cl-induced membrane conductance in the generated SLC4A11WT, SLC4A11MU and SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC lines. Cell barrier function in SLC4A11WT and SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC were assessed by electric cell-substrate impedance sensing (ECIS). Immunostaining was performed to determine the subcellular localization of SLC4A11 protein in the generated SLC4A11WT and SLC4A11MU CEnC lines and human primary CEnC. SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC and the majority of the SLC4A11MU CEnC lines exhibited significantly increased migration rates, altered proliferation, and decreased cell viability under oxidative stress compared to SLC4A11WT CEnC. Induction with 10mM NH4Cl led SLC4A11WT CEnC to depolarize; conversely, SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC hyperpolarized and the majority of SLC4A11MU CEnC either hyperpolarized or had minimal membrane potential changes following NH4Cl induction. Based on ECIS modeling, SLC4A11WT CEnC demonstrated increased cell-substrate adhesion and membrane capacitances compared to SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC. Immunostaining of primary CEnC and SLC4A11WT CEnC lines for SLC4A11 demonstrated predominately cell surface staining with partial colocalization with mitochondrial marker COX4 within punctate subcellular structures. SLC4A11MU CEnC lines also displayed mainly cell surface staining of SLC4A11, except for SLC4A11MU c.2263C&amp;gt;T CEnC, which exhibited mostly perinuclear staining.    CHED- and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations likely lead to CEnC dysfunction, and ultimately CHED and FECD4, by interfering with cell migration, proliferation, viability, membrane conductance, barrier function, and/or cell surface localization of the SLC4A11 protein in CEnC.  This abstract was presented at the 2022 ARVO Annual Meeting, held in Denver, CO, May 1-4, 2022, and virtually.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 20:19:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/chung2022.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/chung2022.html</guid>
        
        <category>CHED</category>
        
        <category>endothelial corneal dystrophy</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR-Cas9</category>
        
        <category>SLC4A11</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Light Adaptation of Retinal Rod Bipolar Cells
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jneurosci.org/lookup/doi/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0444-23.2023&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sensitivity of retinal cells is altered in background light to optimize the detection of contrast. For scotopic (rod) vision, substantial adaptation occurs in the first two cells, the rods and rod bipolar cells (RBCs), through sensitivity adjustments in rods and postsynaptic modulation of the transduction cascade in RBCs. To study the mechanisms mediating these components of adaptation, we made whole-cell, voltage-clamp recordings from retinal slices of mice from both sexes. Adaptation was assessed by fitting the Hill equation to response-intensity relationships with the parameters of half-maximal response (( I_{1/2} )), Hill coefficient (( n )), and maximum response amplitude (( R_{\text{max}} )). We show that rod sensitivity decreases in backgrounds according to the Weber-Fechner relation with an ( I_{1/2} ) of (\sim 50 \, R^* \, \text{s}^{-1}). The sensitivity of RBCs follows a near-identical function, indicating that changes in RBC sensitivity in backgrounds bright enough to adapt the rods are mostly derived from the rods themselves. Backgrounds too dim to adapt the rods can, however, alter ( n ), relieving a synaptic nonlinearity likely through entry of ( \text{Ca}^{2+} ) into the RBCs. There is also a surprising decrease of ( R_{\text{max}} ), indicating that a step in RBC synaptic transduction is desensitized or that the transduction channels became reluctant to open. This effect is greatly reduced after dialysis of BAPTA at a membrane potential of +50 mV to impede ( \text{Ca}^{2+} ) entry. Thus the effects of background illumination in RBCs are in part the result of processes intrinsic to the photoreceptors and in part derive from additional ( \text{Ca}^{2+} )-dependent processes at the first synapse of vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SIGNIFICANCE STATEMENT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light adaptation adjusts the sensitivity of vision as ambient illumination changes. Adaptation for scotopic (rod) vision is known to occur partly in the rods and partly in the rest of the retina from presynaptic and postsynaptic mechanisms. We recorded light responses of rods and rod bipolar cells to identify different components of adaptation and study their mechanisms. We show that bipolar-cell sensitivity largely follows adaptation of the rods but that light too dim to adapt the rods produces a linearization of the bipolar-cell response and a surprising decrease in maximum response amplitude, both mediated by a change in intracellular ( \text{Ca}^{2+} ). These findings provide a new understanding of how the retina responds to changing illumination.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:01:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/Griffis2023.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/Griffis2023.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Novel Role for UNC119 as an Enhancer of Synaptic Transmission
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdpi.com/1422-0067/24/9/8106&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mammalian UNC119 is a ciliary trafficking chaperone highly expressed in the inner segment of retinal photoreceptors. Previous research has shown that UNC119 can bind to transducin, the synaptic ribbon protein RIBEYE, and the calcium-binding protein CaBP4, suggesting that UNC119 may have a role in synaptic transmission. We made patch-clamp recordings from retinal slices in mice with the UNC119 gene deleted and showed that removal of even one gene of UNC119 has no effect on the rod outer segment photocurrent, but acted on bipolar cells much like background light: it depolarized membrane potential, decreased sensitivity, accelerated response decay, and decreased the Hill coefficient of the response-intensity relationship. Similar effects were seen on rod bipolar-cell current and voltage responses, and after exposure to bright light to translocate transducin into the rod inner segment. These findings indicate that UNC119 deletion reduces the steady-state glutamate release rate at rod synapses, though no change in the voltage dependence of the synaptic Ca current was detected. We conclude that UNC119, either by itself or together with transducin, can facilitate the release of glutamate at rod synapses, probably by some interaction with RIBEYE or other synaptic proteins rather than by binding to CaBP4 or calcium channels.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:01:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/Fehlhaber2023.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/Fehlhaber2023.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project Scientist in Vision Science</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Led 1 experimental and 1 in silico project investigating the molecular origin of photoreceptor discrete- and continuous-noise (2 firstauthor
manuscripts in final preparations).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined machine learning methods with electrophysiological recordings of single-photon responses to identify phosphodiesterase as
the driver for photon-detection limits in rod photoreceptors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentored and trained a small team of post doc and staff research personnel on custom acquisition hardware, analysis software, and
data analysis theory and methodology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/project.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/project.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ph.D. Molecular, Cellular, And Integrative Physiology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thesis Title:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mechanisms of detection sensitivity and adaptation in the rod visual pathway.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/phd.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/phd.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mechanisms of detection sensitivity and adaptation in the rod visual pathway</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/4tt400wt&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vision begins in the retina, where photoreceptors have the
task of discriminating incomingphotons from intrinsic cellular
noise. Vertebrates have evolved a duplex retina, in which rod and
cone photoreceptors respond over a broad range of light intensities
from single photons to bright light. Rods evolved from less
sensitive cone-like photoreceptors and are responsible for mediating
the lowest 8 orders of magnitude of light intensity. At the lowest
threshold of vision, rods detect single photons and transmit signals
to downstream neurons in a specialized circuit. In the rod visual
pathway, tens of rods converge onto a single rod bipolar cell, where
noise from the rods is filtered, and rod signals are processed for
further downstream transmission. It is unclear which evolutionary
changes imparted such sensitivity to rods, and how these advantages
allow for rods to discriminate single photons from intrinsic noise.
In downstream bipolar cells, the mechanism for setting the filtering
threshold is unknown. Further, it is unclear what implications of
the thresholding of rod bipolar cells have on vision in scotopic
light levels. In this thesis, I investigated the mechanisms that
work together to define the threshold of vision. To gain
understanding of the nature of vision at the absolute threshold, I
worked with three main goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 1: Determine the set of changes that make feasible 
the incredible sensitivity of rods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 2: Assess contributions of transduction proteins to the
detection of single photons versus intrinsic noise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 3: Measure the ability of rod bipolar cells to shape and parse rod
signals over several orders of magnitude of ambient light levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve these goals, I collected single-cell electrophysiological
from mouse rods and rod bipolar cells. I analyzed the data with
statistical models to determine parameters that described the
mechanisms of visual threshold and adaptation. I also used
statistical modeling to help validate results of mathematical
modeling from our collaborators in the Reingruber Lab (Paris,
France), which show that the important differences between rods and
cones are reflected in the cone as a reduced outer segment volume, a
decreased amplification through the transduction cascade, a faster
turnover rate of the cyclic guanosine monophosphate second
messenger, and an accelerated rate of decay of the phosphodiesterase
(PDE) enzyme (goal 1). Through analysis of intrinsic noise in rods,
I showed that PDE is the critical transduction element both setting
the noise level and limiting the detection threshold and variability
for single-photon absorptions (goal 2). Further, measurements in rod
bipolar cells revealed that rod bipolar cells have a
calcium-dependent feedback mechanism that allows rod bipolar cells
to respond robustly to single-photon absorptions in the minority of
the rods, while continuing to signal in brighter backgrounds that
also cause rod adaptation (goal 3). Taken together, my work has
helped delineate the fundamental mechanisms of signal detection and
processing at the threshold of vision and over the dynamic range of
rod vision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022b.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022b.html</guid>
        
        <category>visual neuroscience</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        <category>photon detection</category>
        
        <category>adaptation</category>
        
        <category>dynamical modeling</category>
        
        <category>software design</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
