<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Khris Griffis, Ph.D.</title>
    <description>Neurophysiology | Statistics | Biosignals Analysis | Data Science</description>
    <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://khrisgriffis.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 12:16:25 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 12:16:25 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rod bipolar cell contributions to changes in response  sensitivity during light adaptation
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iovs.arvojournals.org/article.aspx?articleid=2775580&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;Purpose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mammalian rod bipolar cells desensitize with
increases in mean luminance. This process of light adaptation
reflects the sum of presynaptic gain changes in rods and
postsynaptic changes in the mGluR6 signaling cascade. Here we
dissect these contributions and study their underlying mechanism by
measuring the properties of light-evoked signals in both rods and
rod bipolar cells using patch electrodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were made from rod photoreceptors and rod
bipolar cells in dark-adapted mouse retinal slices. Light-evoked
responses were recorded for a series of flashes in darkness and
during the presentation of background light up to 400 Rh*
(activated rhodopsins) rod&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; sec&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. A Hill 
equation with three free parameters was fit to the rod bipolar cell 
response-intensity relationship - including the maximum photocurrent (Rmax), 
the half-maximal flash strength (&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;), and the extent of nonlinearity in
response amplitude as a function of flash strength (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rod photoreceptors exhibited a 2-fold loss of sensitivity at light
intensities that cause ~50 Rh* sec&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Downstream rod bipolar
cells exhibit a more complicated sensitivity change. In dim
backgrounds, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; was reduced from a value of 1.6 in darkness to 1.0 by
~10 Rh* rod&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; sec&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. At brighter light 
intensities, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; began to shift, reflecting the decline in rod sensitivity. 
Rmax was also reduced by up to 60% at the brightest backgrounds tested.
Dialysis of 10mM BAPTA during recordings, or holding the membrane
potential at +50mV, reduced this modulation. Nonstationary noise
analysis of the falling phase of light-evoked responses elicited in
darkness and in background light reveal that the reduction in Rmax
does not arise from a reduced TRPM1 single-channel current. Instead,
it must result from a reduction in the coupling between the mGluR6
receptors and TRPM1 channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measurements in mouse rod bipolar cells reveal that the loss in sensitivity 
as a function of background light is a combination of the loss in sensitivity 
due to rod phototransduction, along with mechanisms intrinsic to the rod
bipolar cell dendrites. These collectively allow rod bipolar cells
to respond robustly to single photon absorptions in a minority of
the rods, while continuing the signal at brighter lights that also
cause rod adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a 2021 ARVO Annual Meeting abstract.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 20:19:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2021.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2021.html</guid>
        
        <category>vision science</category>
        
        <category>rod bipolar cells</category>
        
        <category>light adaptation</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        <category>statistical modeling</category>
        
        <category>metabotropic glutamate signaling</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investigation of the functional impact of CHED- and FECD4-associated  SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iovs.arvojournals.org/article.aspx?articleid=2781541&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To characterize the impact of SLC4A11 mutations associated with congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED) and Fuchs endothelial corneal dystrophy type 4 (FECD4) on corneal endothelial cell (CEnC) function and SLC4A11 protein localization.    Human SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC lines were generated by CRISPR-Cas9 mediated gene editing. SLC4A11 wildtype (SLC4A11WT) and SLC4A11 mutant (SLC4A11MU) human CEnC lines were generated by stable transduction with lentiviruses containing either SLC4A11WT or SLC4A11MU expression vectors harboring CHED-/FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations (CHED: c.374G&amp;gt;A, c.1813C&amp;gt;T, c.2263C&amp;gt;T; FECD4: c.2224G&amp;gt;A). Functional assays were performed to assess cell migration, proliferation, viability after induced oxidative stress and NH4Cl-induced membrane conductance in the generated SLC4A11WT, SLC4A11MU and SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC lines. Cell barrier function in SLC4A11WT and SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC were assessed by electric cell-substrate impedance sensing (ECIS). Immunostaining was performed to determine the subcellular localization of SLC4A11 protein in the generated SLC4A11WT and SLC4A11MU CEnC lines and human primary CEnC. SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC and the majority of the SLC4A11MU CEnC lines exhibited significantly increased migration rates, altered proliferation, and decreased cell viability under oxidative stress compared to SLC4A11WT CEnC. Induction with 10mM NH4Cl led SLC4A11WT CEnC to depolarize; conversely, SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC hyperpolarized and the majority of SLC4A11MU CEnC either hyperpolarized or had minimal membrane potential changes following NH4Cl induction. Based on ECIS modeling, SLC4A11WT CEnC demonstrated increased cell-substrate adhesion and membrane capacitances compared to SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC. Immunostaining of primary CEnC and SLC4A11WT CEnC lines for SLC4A11 demonstrated predominately cell surface staining with partial colocalization with mitochondrial marker COX4 within punctate subcellular structures. SLC4A11MU CEnC lines also displayed mainly cell surface staining of SLC4A11, except for SLC4A11MU c.2263C&amp;gt;T CEnC, which exhibited mostly perinuclear staining.    CHED- and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations likely lead to CEnC dysfunction, and ultimately CHED and FECD4, by interfering with cell migration, proliferation, viability, membrane conductance, barrier function, and/or cell surface localization of the SLC4A11 protein in CEnC.  This abstract was presented at the 2022 ARVO Annual Meeting, held in Denver, CO, May 1-4, 2022, and virtually.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 20:19:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/chung2022.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/chung2022.html</guid>
        
        <category>CHED</category>
        
        <category>endothelial corneal dystrophy</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR-Cas9</category>
        
        <category>SLC4A11</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project Scientist in Vision Science</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Led 1 experimental and 1 in silico project investigating the molecular origin of photoreceptor discrete- and continuous-noise (2 firstauthor
manuscripts in final preparations).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined machine learning methods with electrophysiological recordings of single-photon responses to identify phosphodiesterase as
the driver for photon-detection limits in rod photoreceptors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentored and trained a small team of post doc and staff research personnel on custom acquisition hardware, analysis software, and
data analysis theory and methodology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/project.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/project.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ph.D. Molecular, Cellular, And Integrative Physiology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thesis Title:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mechanisms of detection sensitivity and adaptation in the rod visual pathway.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/phd.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/phd.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mechanisms of detection sensitivity and adaptation in the rod visual pathway</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/4tt400wt&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vision begins in the retina, where photoreceptors have the
task of discriminating incomingphotons from intrinsic cellular
noise. Vertebrates have evolved a duplex retina, in which rod and
cone photoreceptors respond over a broad range of light intensities
from single photons to bright light. Rods evolved from less
sensitive cone-like photoreceptors and are responsible for mediating
the lowest 8 orders of magnitude of light intensity. At the lowest
threshold of vision, rods detect single photons and transmit signals
to downstream neurons in a specialized circuit. In the rod visual
pathway, tens of rods converge onto a single rod bipolar cell, where
noise from the rods is filtered, and rod signals are processed for
further downstream transmission. It is unclear which evolutionary
changes imparted such sensitivity to rods, and how these advantages
allow for rods to discriminate single photons from intrinsic noise.
In downstream bipolar cells, the mechanism for setting the filtering
threshold is unknown. Further, it is unclear what implications of
the thresholding of rod bipolar cells have on vision in scotopic
light levels. In this thesis, I investigated the mechanisms that
work together to define the threshold of vision. To gain
understanding of the nature of vision at the absolute threshold, I
worked with three main goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 1: Determine the set of changes that make feasible 
the incredible sensitivity of rods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 2: Assess contributions of transduction proteins to the
detection of single photons versus intrinsic noise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 3: Measure the ability of rod bipolar cells to shape and parse rod
signals over several orders of magnitude of ambient light levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve these goals, I collected single-cell electrophysiological
from mouse rods and rod bipolar cells. I analyzed the data with
statistical models to determine parameters that described the
mechanisms of visual threshold and adaptation. I also used
statistical modeling to help validate results of mathematical
modeling from our collaborators in the Reingruber Lab (Paris,
France), which show that the important differences between rods and
cones are reflected in the cone as a reduced outer segment volume, a
decreased amplification through the transduction cascade, a faster
turnover rate of the cyclic guanosine monophosphate second
messenger, and an accelerated rate of decay of the phosphodiesterase
(PDE) enzyme (goal 1). Through analysis of intrinsic noise in rods,
I showed that PDE is the critical transduction element both setting
the noise level and limiting the detection threshold and variability
for single-photon absorptions (goal 2). Further, measurements in rod
bipolar cells revealed that rod bipolar cells have a
calcium-dependent feedback mechanism that allows rod bipolar cells
to respond robustly to single-photon absorptions in the minority of
the rods, while continuing to signal in brighter backgrounds that
also cause rod adaptation (goal 3). Taken together, my work has
helped delineate the fundamental mechanisms of signal detection and
processing at the threshold of vision and over the dynamic range of
rod vision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022b.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022b.html</guid>
        
        <category>visual neuroscience</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        <category>photon detection</category>
        
        <category>adaptation</category>
        
        <category>dynamical modeling</category>
        
        <category>software design</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Circadian and ultradian rhythms in normal mice and in a mouse model of Huntington&apos;s disease
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/07420528.2021.2014516&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circadian rhythms in core body temperature (CBT) have been
widely studied, but fewer studies have explored higher-frequency
(ultradian) rhythms in detail. We analyzed CBT recordings from young
and middle-aged wild-type mice as well as from the Q175 model of
Huntington’s disease (HD), at sufficient temporal resolution to
address the question of ultradian rhythms. We used model selection
methods to show that the overall circadian pattern was better fit by
a square wave than a sine wave. Then, using Fourier analysis of the
CBT rhythms, we identified the spectral signature of an 8-hour
oscillation that occurs in the night but not the day, an observation
that can be confirmed by direct inspection of the rhythms. This
diurnal amplitude modulation of the 8-hour rhythm was lost with
aging as well as in the HD model. Thus, the impact of aging and
disease is seen here in the loss of the ability to separate rhythms
into a daytime phase and a nighttime phase. These findings raise the
possibility that ultradian rhythms in CBT may be a useful biomarker
for the pathology within the central nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:01:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022a.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022a.html</guid>
        
        <category>circadian rhythms</category>
        
        <category>ultradian rhythms</category>
        
        <category>Fourier analysis</category>
        
        <category>biosignals analysis</category>
        
        <category>Huntington\&apos;s disease</category>
        
        <category>aging</category>
        
        <category>biomarker</category>
        
        <category>core body temperature</category>
        
        <category>physiological oscillations</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Energy shortage in human and mouse models of SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1167/iovs.61.8.39&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To elucidate the molecular events in solute carrier family 4 member 11 (SLC4A11)-deficient corneal endothelium that lead to the endothelial dysfunction that characterizes the dystrophies associated with SLC4A11 mutations, congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED) and Fuchs endothelial corneal dystrophy 4. Comparative transcriptomic analysis (CTA) was performed in primary human corneal endothelial cells (pHCEnC) and murine corneal endothelial cells (MCEnC) with normal and reduced levels of SLC4A11 (SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC) and Slc4a11 (Slc4a11−/− MCEnC), respectively. Validation of differentially expressed genes was performed using immunofluorescence staining of CHED corneal endothelium, as well as western blot and quantitative PCR analysis of SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC and Slc4a11−/− MCEnC. Functional analyses were performed to investigate potential functional changes associated with the observed transcriptomic alterations. CTA revealed inhibition of cell metabolism and ion transport function as well as mitochondrial dysfunction, leading to reduced adenosine triphosphate (ATP) production, in SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC and Slc4a11−/− MCEnC. Co-localization of SNARE protein STX17 with mitochondria marker COX4 was observed in CHED corneal endothelium, as was activation of AMPK–p53/ULK1 in both SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC and Slc4a11−/− MCEnC, providing additional evidence of mitochondrial dysfunction and mitophagy. Reduced Na+-dependent HCO3− transport activity and altered NH4Cl-induced membrane potential changes were observed in Slc4a11−/− MCEnC. Reduced steady-state ATP levels and subsequent activation of the AMPK–p53 pathway provide a link between the metabolic functional deficit and transcriptome alterations, as well as evidence of insufficient ATP to maintain the Na+/K+-ATPase corneal endothelial pump as the cause of the edema that characterizes SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/zhang2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/zhang2020.html</guid>
        
        <category>CHED</category>
        
        <category>endothelial corneal dystrophy</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR-Cas9</category>
        
        <category>SLC4A11</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A kinetic analysis of mouse rod and cone photoreceptor responses</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://physoc.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1113/JP279524&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most vertebrates have rod and cone photoreceptors, which
differ in their sensitivity and response kinetics. We know that rods
evolved from cone-like precursors through the expression of
different transduction genes or the same genes at different levels,
but we do not know which molecular differences were most important.
We have approached this problem in mouse retina by analysing the
kinetic differences between rod flash responses and recent
voltage-clamp recordings of cone flash responses, using a model
incorporating the principal features of photoreceptor transduction.
We apply a novel method of analysis using the log-transform of the
current, and we ask which of the model’s dynamic parameters need be
changed to transform the flash response of a rod into that of a
cone. The most important changes are a decrease in the gain of the
response, reflecting a reduction in amplification of the
transduction cascade; an increase in the rate of turnover of cGMP in
darkness; and an increase in the rate of decay of activated
phosphodiesterase, with perhaps also an increase in the rate of
decay of light-activated visual pigment. Although we cannot exclude
other differences, and in particular alterations in the Ca2+ economy
of the photoreceptors, we believe that we have identified the
kinetic parameters principally responsible for the differences in
the flash responses of the two kinds of photoreceptors, which were
likely during evolution to have resulted in the duplex retina.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/reingruber2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/reingruber2020.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evidence of axon connectivity across a spinal cord transection in rats treated with epidural stimulation and motor training combined with olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation.
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.expneurol.2018.07.015&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olfactory ensheathing cells (OECs) are unique glia that
support axon outgrowth in the olfactory system, and when used as
cellular therapy after spinal cord injury, improve recovery and axon
regeneration. Here we assessed the effects of combining OEC
transplantation with another promising therapy, epidural electrical
stimulation during a rehabilitative motor task. Sprague-Dawley rats
received a mid-thoracic transection and transplantation of OECs or
fibroblasts (FBs) followed by lumbar stimulation while climbing an
inclined grid. We injected pseudorabies virus (PRV) into hindlimb
muscles 7-months post-injury to assess connectivity across the
transection. Analyses showed that the number of serotonergic (5-HT)
axons that crossed the rostral scar border and the area of
neurofilament-positive axons in the injury site were both greater in
OEC- than FB-treated rats. We detected PRV-labeled cells rostral to
the transection and remarkable evidence of 5-HT and PRV axons
crossing the injury site in 1 OEC- and 1 FB-treated rat. The axons
that crossed suggested either axon regeneration (OEC) or small areas
of probable tissue sparing (FB). Most PRV-labeled thoracic neurons
were detected in laminae VII or X, and ~25% expressed Chx10, a
marker for V2a interneurons. These findings suggest potential
regeneration or sparing of circuits that connect thoracic
interneurons to lumbar somatic motor neurons. Despite evidence of
axonal connectivity, no behavioral changes were detected in this
small-scale study. Together these data suggest that when
supplemented with epidural stimulation and climbing, OEC
transplantation can increase axonal growth across the injury site
and may promote recovery of propriospinal circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/thornton2018.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/thornton2018.html</guid>
        
        <category>spinal cord injury</category>
        
        <category>immunohistochemsitry</category>
        
        <category>olfactory glia</category>
        
        <category>neural repair</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Calcium oscillations in human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells\: Developing a hierarchical clustering method for analysis and the effects of IL-1b
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1096/fasebj.2018.32.1_supplement.628.1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rationale&quot;&gt;Rationale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is
characterized by lung inflammation, edema, and severe hypoxemia. In
previous work, we showed that IL-1b is required for the development
of severe hypoxemia in a murine model of acute lung injury,
independent of measures of inflammation and edema. We hypothesized
that IL-1b is altering the regulation of pulmonary blood flow to
cause severe V/Q mismatching in acute lung injury. To explore
possible mechanisms for this, we studied the effects of IL-1b on
calcium flux in human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells (hPASMCs)
in response to the vasoconstrictor endothelin-1 (ET-1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;hPASMCs were grown on glass bottom dishes to confluence and some
dishes were treated with IL-1b (10ng/mL) for 3h. Cells were loaded
with 5mM Cal-520 and stimulated with ET-1 (10nM) during fluorescent
imaging on a Zeiss LSM confocal microscope. All cells from each
field were individually selected using Fiji image analysis software.
By visual inspection, we noticed that a marked number of cells
showed oscillations in calcium flux after ET-1. To quantify
oscillatory from non-oscillatory responses, we used a mixture of
information theoretic and machine learning algorithms and developed
a custom classifier tool. We applied this tool to our control and
IL-1b-treated data (Figure 1) and created a contingency table for
the effects of IL-1b on the induction of oscillatory responses. $\chi^2$
confidence intervals and statistical significance were computed by
bootstrap simulation with $10^5$ replicates using custom scripts in
R(v3.4.1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In control dishes (n = 6), there were a total of
444 non-oscillators cells and 379 oscillator cells. In dishes
treated with IL-1b (n = 2), there were 50 non-oscillator cells and
211 oscillators total. A bootstrap simulation based $\chi^2$ test was
performed and a strong relationship was found between IL-1b
treatment and the presence of oscillatory responses, 
$\chi^2 = 96.7(71.2, 125.5; 95\% C.I.)$, $p&amp;lt;10^{-5}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support or Funding Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nat’l Heart, Lung &amp;amp; Blood Inst. K08HL125806&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This abstract is from the Experimental Biology 2018 Meeting. There is no full 
text article associated with this abstract published in The FASEB Journal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/kim2018.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/kim2018.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
