<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Khris Griffis, Ph.D.</title>
    <description>Neurophysiology | Statistics | Biosignals Analysis | Data Science</description>
    <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://khrisgriffis.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 14:57:53 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 14:57:53 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Essentially Me</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;essentially-me&quot;&gt;Essentially Me&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;!-- Einstein quote --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most beautiful thing we can experience is the mysterious. It is the source of all true art and science. He to whom this emotion is a stranger, who can no longer pause to wonder and stand rapt in awe, is as good as dead: his eyes are closed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#Einstein1930&quot;&gt;Einstein, 1930&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!-- welcome --&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Hello, I’m so glad you found this page. My name is Khris. I have a Ph.D. from the University of California, Los Angles, in the field of Molecular, Cellular, and Integrative Physiology. My area of expertise is in visual neuroscience. My &lt;a href=&quot;../publications/griffis2022b.html&quot;&gt;doctoral work&lt;/a&gt; investigated molecular mechanisms of photon detection and processing in the mammalian rod visual pathway (&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#griffis2022mechanisms&quot;&gt;Griffis, 2022&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- tl;dr --&gt;

&lt;!-- personal statement-ish --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-scientific-journey&quot;&gt;My Scientific Journey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Following my undergraduate degree in Physiological Science (UCLA), I joined the field of neurodegenerative repair, focusing on spinal-cord injury research in the lab of Patricia E. Phelps at UCLA. Beginning in 2011, I focused primarily on the potential benefit of olfactory ensheathing cells (OECs) as an &lt;em&gt;in vitro&lt;/em&gt; model of spinal cord injury, and I collaborated on 3 projects assessing the therapeutic effects of OEC engraftments on neural regeneration. In 2013, I began the Master of Science degree in the Department of Integrative Biology and Physiology at UCLA and was able to continue my work in neural repair. Throughout my tenure in the Phelps lab, I had the opportunity to familiarize myself with several biological tools, including bench work from PCR, western-blot, and immunohistochemistry to cell imaging, cell culture, histology, and cryostat slicing. I managed upwards of 4 rodent colonies as the principle lead of animal husbandry, where I selectively maintained the colonies based on a desired level of expression of transgenic DNA, which I assessed by biochemical methods, e.g., by PCR. I worked closely with the UCLA Department of Laboratory Animal Medicine as the first line of vetinary needs for these colonies. Employing my love for statistics, and my hobby of computer science&lt;a href=&quot;#fn_1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I developed novel analysis methods with Python, R, and MATLAB, to assess the extent of neural circuitry regeneration after spinal transection from electromyographical, transcranial, and spinal epidural electrical recordings. I took advantage of the opportunity to deepen my understanding of electronic circuits, and how they parallel with biological signals, by working with post-doctoral researchers in Dr. Reggie Edgerton’s lab at UCLA and our collaborators at CalTech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;When I began spinal-cord research, I was most interested in neural connections and the complex circuitry they form. I decided that no biological system is better suited to ask questions of this nature than vision, specifically, the retina. To my great fortune, right there at UCLA was a world renowned photoreceptor physiologist, Dr. Gordon Fain, and his highly successful and brilliant disciple, Dr. Alapakkam “Sam” Sampath. I sought to join Dr. Sampath’s lab with success and I began my Ph.D. journey in the Spring of 2016. The Sampath lab was an environment comprised of experienced students, post-doctoral researchers, and a wealth of collaborators across the globe, and I quickly became a part of the team. At the time I joined the lab, Sam had recently moved from the Keck School of Medicine (USC) to UCLA and, albeit functional for experiments, the lab was in the process of upgrading our physiology rigs and waiting for the Jules Stein Eye Institute to finish remodeling so the lab could move to its final location. I was able to use my hardware and software experience to upgrade the existing acquisition systems and to build new light stimulus pathways. In 2017, the lab moved to the Jules Stein building and I was fortunate enough to build my own rig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;Over my tenure in the Sampath lab, I developed novel methods for analyzing time-series, electrophysiological data. I contributed to mathematical modeling of photoreceptor light responses, where I leveraged the power of resampling statistics for model selection, uncertainty quantification and parameter estimation. I contributed to an open source software acquisition system and wrote a MATLAB-based application to visualize and analyze electrophysiological data offline. Aside from the technical work, I contributed to 8 collaborations, from which 4 separate NIH grants were awarded, 4 manuscripts were published (1 more in preparation as of 2023-04-20 00:00:00 -0700), and several conference proceedings were published (&lt;em&gt;for example:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#chung2022investigation&quot;&gt;Chung &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt;, 2022; Kim &lt;i&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt;, 2018&lt;/a&gt;). Below, I’ve detailed my contributions to science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- contributios to science --&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scientific-contributions-to-date&quot;&gt;Scientific Contributions (to date)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;During my time in the laboratory of Patricia E. Phelps, I focused primarily on investigating the therapeutic potential of OECs in regenerating functional circuits following complete spinal cord injury. As a consequence of my technical background and my multiple roles within the lab, I was able to contribute to several projects with collaborators. During my tenure in the lab of Alapakkam Sampath, I was fortunate to leverage my technical background and my passion for math and statistics to contribute novel research and expand understanding of light detection and processing in the retina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;text-justify&quot;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A major contributing factor to any cellular transplant therapy is that of cell survival. By using intrinsic labeling in commercially available, eGFP transgenic Sprague Dawley rats, I assisted in generating OEC primary cultures that we transplanted into age-matched female Sprague Dawley rats which had received spinal cord injury. Using immunohistochemical and stereological methods, I quantified the amount of surviving control fibroblasts or OECs 1, 2, and 4 weeks post-injury and assessed the extent of serotonergic (5-HT) axon die back. I also organized and assisted in the surgical implantation of transcranial stimulation electrodes, electromyographic recording electrodes, and cellular implants. Using transcranial stimulation to evoke descending potentials and assess potential regenerated connectivity, I helped evaluate rats at 2 and 7 months after injury. We found that training, spinal cord stimulation, and OEC treatment yielded moderate functional recovery in spinal transected rats.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;R. R. Khankan, &lt;em&gt;K. G. Griffis&lt;/em&gt;, I. B. Wanner, H. Zhong, R. R. Roy, V. R. Edgerton, P. E. Phelps. Survival and migration of adult rat eGFP-OECs after a complete spinal cord transection. Program No. 466.02. 2013 Neuroscience Meeting Planner. San Diego, CA: Society for Neuroscience, 2013. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A. K. Yeung, G. Garcia-Alias, &lt;em&gt;K. G. Griffis&lt;/em&gt;, R. R. Khankan, H. Zhong, *R. R. Roy, P. E. Phelps, V. Edgerton. Spinal cord epidural stimulation and climb training enhance axon regeneration in rats transplanted with olfactory ensheathing cells after a complete spinal cord transection. Neuroscience 2015 Abstracts. Chicago, IL: Society for Neuroscience, 2015. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Following the cell viability experiments, I hypothesized that transplanted OECs affected glial scar formation in a potentially beneficial way. Using immunohistochemistry and confocal microscopy, I evaluated astrocyte morphology around the lesion, as well as the presence of activated microglia and invading macrophages. We showed that, compared to control fibroblast treated rats, the acute immune response and the deposition of CS-56+ proteins were markedly reduced in OEC treated rats at all acute time points following injury. We determined that OECs reduce lesion size in early acute responses, but by 8 weeks these effects, along with the OECs, are diminished. Further, 5-HT+ axons were more abundant in OEC treated rats, implying that OECs modulate the immune response to facilitate axonal regeneration. The evolution of this project produced two abstracts and two manuscripts in 2016 and 2018.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Thornton, M. A., Mehta, M. D., Morad, T. T., Ingraham, K. L., Khankan, R. R., Griffis, K. G., Yeung, A. K., Zhong, H., Roy, R. R., Edgerton, V. R., &amp;amp; Phelps, P. E. (2018). Evidence of axon connectivity across a spinal cord transection in rats treated with epidural stimulation and motor training combined with olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation. Experimental Neurology, 309, 119–133. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.EXPNEUROL.2018.07.015&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Khankan, R. R., Griffis, K. G., Haggerty-Skeans, J. R., Zhong, H., Roy, R. R., Reggie Edgerton, V., &amp;amp; Phelps, P. E. (2016). Olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation after a complete spinal cord transection mediates neuroprotective and immunomodulatory mechanisms to facilitate regeneration. Journal of Neuroscience, 36(23). https://doi.org/10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0085-16.2016&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Khankan, R.R., Ingraham, K.L., Haggerty-Skeans, J.R., Griffis, K.G., Zhong, H., Roy,R., Edgerton, V.R., Phelps, P.E. Olfactory ensheathing cells reduce inhibitory factors at the astroglial scar-border after a complete mid-thoracic spinal cord transection. Program No. 338.07/V24 Neuroscience 2015 Abstracts. Chicago, IL: Society for Neuroscience, 2015. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;R. R. Khankan, K. G. Griffis, D. N. Perez, J. R. Haggerty-Skeans, H. Zhong, R. R. Roy, V. R. Edgerton, *P. E. Phelps. Olfactory ensheathing cells and fibroblasts differ their modification of the lesion site after complete spinal cord transection. Program No. 422.26. 2014 Neuroscience Meeting Planner. Washington, DC: Society for Neuroscience, 2014. Online.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I became interested in cellular physiology and had the opportunity to use both my cell-culture experience and statistical knowledge to assist a colleague in studying the role of calcium oscillations in a module of acute lung injury of human pulmonary artery smooth muscle cells (hPASMCs). To study possible mechanisms, we investigated effects of IL-1b on calcium flux in hPASMCs in response to vasoconstrictor endothelin-1. I developed an analysis method, using machine learning and other statistical methods, to identify oscillating and non-oscillating responders. We showed that IL-1b is strongly associated with increases in oscillating responders. Follow-up work from this project is ongoing, and a manuscript is in preparation.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Elizabeth H. Kim, Khris G. Griffis, Meredith Sheppard, Suliman Alamro, Daniel Tabari, Alan Garfinkel, and Heather D. Jones. Calcium Oscillations in Human Pulmonary Artery Smooth Muscle Cells: Developing a Hierarchical Clustering Method for Analysis and the Effects of IL-1b. The FASEB Journal 2018 32:1_supplement, 628.1-628.1&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In a collaboration between the laboratories of Alapakkam Sampath and Anthony J. Aldave, I did whole-cell patch recordings on isolated mouse corneal endothelial cells in culture to study the functional role of SLC4A11 in a murine model of congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED). SCL4A11 is essential for facilitating energy producing glutaminolysis, maintaining antioxidant signaling, and preventing apoptosis in corneal endothelial cells. We showed that reduced steady-state ATP levels and subsequent activation of the AMPK-p53 pathway provide a link between the metabolic functional deficit and transcriptome alterations. We also found evidence that insufficient ATP to maintain the Na+/K+-ATPase corneal endothelial pump is the cause of the edema that characterizes SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Zhang, W., Frausto, R., Chung, D.D., Griffis, C.G., Kao, L., Chen, A., Azimov, R., Sampath, A.P., Kurtz, I., Aldave, A.J.   (2020)  Energy shortage in human and mouse models of SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies .  Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science,  61(8),  39.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Chung, D., Chen, A., Choo, C., Zhang, W., Griffis, C., Bonezzi, P., Sampath, A.P., Aldave, A.J.   (2022)  Investigation of the functional impact of CHED- and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells .  Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science,  63(7),  3624-A0189.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I provided patch-clamp recordings from rod photoreceptors and statistical analysis to a model of mouse cone photoreceptors developed by Jürgen Reingruber and Gordon Fain. I helped to show that the kinetic changes that transform the rod response into that of the cone are characterized by these three key parameters: 1) reduction in transduction amplification, 2) increased dark turnover rate of cGMP, and 3) increased decay rate of activated phosphodiesterase.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reingruber, J., N.T. Ingram, Griffis, K.G., and G.L. Fain. 2020. A kinetic analysis of mouse rod and cone photoreceptor responses. Journal of Physiology, in press.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Extending from the collaboration in which I used information theoretic clustering of calcium oscillations in hPASMCs, I collaborated with Alan Garfinkel and Christopher Colwell to study oscillations in the core body temperature (CBT) of mice with a genetic perturbation (Q175) that mimics Huntington’s disease (HD) in humans. Circadian rhythms in CBT have been widely studied, but fewer studies have explored higher-frequency (ultradian) rhythms in detail. We analyzed CBT recordings from young and middle-aged wild-type mice as well as from the Q175 model of HD, at sufficient temporal resolution to address the question of ultradian rhythms. We used model selection methods to show that the overall circadian pattern was better fit by a square wave than a sine wave. Then, using Fourier analysis of the CBT rhythms, we identified the spectral signature of an 8-hour oscillation that occurs in the night but not the day, an observation that can be confirmed by direct inspection of the rhythms. This diurnal amplitude modulation of the 8-hour rhythm was lost with aging as well as in the HD model. Thus, the impact of aging and disease is seen here in the loss of the ability to separate rhythms into a daytime phase and a nighttime phase. These findings raise the possibility that ultradian rhythms in CBT may be a useful biomarker for the pathology within the central nervous system.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Griffis, C.G., Mistry, J., Islam, K., Cutler, T., Colwell, C.S., Garfinkel, A.   (2022)  Circadian and ultradian rhythms in normal mice and in a mouse model of Huntington’s disease .  Chronobiology international,  39(4),  513-524.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Light adaptation adjusts the sensitivity of vision as ambient illumination changes. Adaptation for scotopic (rod) vision is known to occur partly in the rods and partly in the rest of the retina from presynaptic and postsynaptic mechanisms. We recorded light responses of rods and rod bipolar cells to identify different components of adaptation and study their mechanisms. We show that bipolar-cell sensitivity largely follows adaptation of the rods, but that light too dim to adapt the rods produces a linearization of the bipolar-cell response dynamics and a surprising decrease in maximum response amplitude, both mediated by a change in intracellular Ca2+. These findings provide a new understanding of how the retina responds to changes in ambient illumination.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Khris G. Griffis, Katherine E. Fehlhaber, Fred Rieke, and Alapakkam P. Sampath. (2023). Light adaptation of retinal rod bipolar cells. &lt;em&gt;Submitted to J. Neurosci., pending acceptance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Griffis, C., Sampath, A.P.. (2021)  Rod bipolar cell contributions to changes in response sensitivity during light adaptation .  Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science,  62(8),  2004.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In collaboration with Johan Pahlberg, Ph.D. (NIH/NIDCR), I dissected contributions of transduction-cascade proteins to the continuous noise that obscures the single-photon response in rod photoreceptors and pinpointed the molecular origin of discrete noise, which is indistinguishable from the single-photon response, albeit in the absence of light. To do so, we used novel murine models with graded reductions of G-alpha transducin-1 and PDE-6 levels, and made whole-cell patch recordings in individual rods. Through my experiments, I characterized rod continuous noise and investigated its molecular origin to ask if any one component both sets the continuous noise level and limits the detection of single photons.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Christopher G. Griffis*, Ulisse Bocchero*, Alapakkam P. Sampath and Johan Pahlberg. Origins of discrete and continuous dark noise in rod photoreceptors. &lt;em&gt;In preparation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;fn_1&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size:0.7em;&quot;&gt;1: I was that kid in high school who hacked the brand new windows 98 classroom so the teacher couldn&apos;t see I was playing solitaire instead of practicing typing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Einstein1930&quot;&gt;Einstein, A. (1930) What I Believe: Living Philosophies XIII. &lt;i&gt;Forum and Century&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;b&gt;LXXXIV&lt;/b&gt;, 192.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;griffis2022mechanisms&quot;&gt;Griffis, C.G. (2022) Mechanisms of Detection Sensitivity and Adaptation in the Rod Visual Pathway (PhD thesis).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;chung2022investigation&quot;&gt;Chung, D., Chen, A., Choo, C., Zhang, W., Griffis, C., Bonezzi, P., Sampath, A.P., &amp;amp; Aldave, A.J. (2022) Investigation of the functional impact of CHED-and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells. In &lt;i&gt;Investigative Ophthalmology &amp;amp; Visual Science&lt;/i&gt;. The Association for Research in Vision and Ophthalmology, pp. 3624–A0189.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kim2018calcium&quot;&gt;Kim, E.H., Griffis, K.G., Sheppard, M., Alamro, S., Tabari, D., Garfinkel, A., &amp;amp; Jones, H.D. (2018) Calcium Oscillations in Human Pulmonary Artery Smooth Muscle Cells: Developing a Hierarchical Clustering Method for Analysis and the Effects of IL-1b. In &lt;i&gt;The FASEB Journal&lt;/i&gt;. Wiley Online Library, pp. 628–621.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/missives/EssentiallyMe.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/missives/EssentiallyMe.html</guid>
        
        <category>featured</category>
        
        
        <category>missives</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rod bipolar cell contributions to changes in response  sensitivity during light adaptation
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iovs.arvojournals.org/article.aspx?articleid=2775580&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;purpose&quot;&gt;Purpose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mammalian rod bipolar cells desensitize with
increases in mean luminance. This process of light adaptation
reflects the sum of presynaptic gain changes in rods and
postsynaptic changes in the mGluR6 signaling cascade. Here we
dissect these contributions and study their underlying mechanism by
measuring the properties of light-evoked signals in both rods and
rod bipolar cells using patch electrodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;methods&quot;&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole-cell voltage clamp recordings were made from rod photoreceptors and rod
bipolar cells in dark-adapted mouse retinal slices. Light-evoked
responses were recorded for a series of flashes in darkness and
during the presentation of background light up to 400 Rh*
(activated rhodopsins) rod&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; sec&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. A Hill 
equation with three free parameters was fit to the rod bipolar cell 
response-intensity relationship - including the maximum photocurrent (Rmax), 
the half-maximal flash strength (&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;), and the extent of nonlinearity in
response amplitude as a function of flash strength (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rod photoreceptors exhibited a 2-fold loss of sensitivity at light
intensities that cause ~50 Rh* sec&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. Downstream rod bipolar
cells exhibit a more complicated sensitivity change. In dim
backgrounds, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; was reduced from a value of 1.6 in darkness to 1.0 by
~10 Rh* rod&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; sec&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt;. At brighter light 
intensities, &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; began to shift, reflecting the decline in rod sensitivity. 
Rmax was also reduced by up to 60% at the brightest backgrounds tested.
Dialysis of 10mM BAPTA during recordings, or holding the membrane
potential at +50mV, reduced this modulation. Nonstationary noise
analysis of the falling phase of light-evoked responses elicited in
darkness and in background light reveal that the reduction in Rmax
does not arise from a reduced TRPM1 single-channel current. Instead,
it must result from a reduction in the coupling between the mGluR6
receptors and TRPM1 channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measurements in mouse rod bipolar cells reveal that the loss in sensitivity 
as a function of background light is a combination of the loss in sensitivity 
due to rod phototransduction, along with mechanisms intrinsic to the rod
bipolar cell dendrites. These collectively allow rod bipolar cells
to respond robustly to single photon absorptions in a minority of
the rods, while continuing the signal at brighter lights that also
cause rod adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a 2021 ARVO Annual Meeting abstract.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 20:19:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2021.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2021.html</guid>
        
        <category>vision science</category>
        
        <category>rod bipolar cells</category>
        
        <category>light adaptation</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        <category>statistical modeling</category>
        
        <category>metabotropic glutamate signaling</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investigation of the functional impact of CHED- and FECD4-associated  SLC4A11 mutations in human corneal endothelial cells
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iovs.arvojournals.org/article.aspx?articleid=2781541&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To characterize the impact of SLC4A11 mutations associated with congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED) and Fuchs endothelial corneal dystrophy type 4 (FECD4) on corneal endothelial cell (CEnC) function and SLC4A11 protein localization.    Human SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC lines were generated by CRISPR-Cas9 mediated gene editing. SLC4A11 wildtype (SLC4A11WT) and SLC4A11 mutant (SLC4A11MU) human CEnC lines were generated by stable transduction with lentiviruses containing either SLC4A11WT or SLC4A11MU expression vectors harboring CHED-/FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations (CHED: c.374G&amp;gt;A, c.1813C&amp;gt;T, c.2263C&amp;gt;T; FECD4: c.2224G&amp;gt;A). Functional assays were performed to assess cell migration, proliferation, viability after induced oxidative stress and NH4Cl-induced membrane conductance in the generated SLC4A11WT, SLC4A11MU and SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC lines. Cell barrier function in SLC4A11WT and SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC were assessed by electric cell-substrate impedance sensing (ECIS). Immunostaining was performed to determine the subcellular localization of SLC4A11 protein in the generated SLC4A11WT and SLC4A11MU CEnC lines and human primary CEnC. SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC and the majority of the SLC4A11MU CEnC lines exhibited significantly increased migration rates, altered proliferation, and decreased cell viability under oxidative stress compared to SLC4A11WT CEnC. Induction with 10mM NH4Cl led SLC4A11WT CEnC to depolarize; conversely, SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC hyperpolarized and the majority of SLC4A11MU CEnC either hyperpolarized or had minimal membrane potential changes following NH4Cl induction. Based on ECIS modeling, SLC4A11WT CEnC demonstrated increased cell-substrate adhesion and membrane capacitances compared to SLC4A11&lt;sup&gt;-/-&lt;/sup&gt; CEnC. Immunostaining of primary CEnC and SLC4A11WT CEnC lines for SLC4A11 demonstrated predominately cell surface staining with partial colocalization with mitochondrial marker COX4 within punctate subcellular structures. SLC4A11MU CEnC lines also displayed mainly cell surface staining of SLC4A11, except for SLC4A11MU c.2263C&amp;gt;T CEnC, which exhibited mostly perinuclear staining.    CHED- and FECD4-associated SLC4A11 mutations likely lead to CEnC dysfunction, and ultimately CHED and FECD4, by interfering with cell migration, proliferation, viability, membrane conductance, barrier function, and/or cell surface localization of the SLC4A11 protein in CEnC.  This abstract was presented at the 2022 ARVO Annual Meeting, held in Denver, CO, May 1-4, 2022, and virtually.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 20:19:35 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/chung2022.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/chung2022.html</guid>
        
        <category>CHED</category>
        
        <category>endothelial corneal dystrophy</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR-Cas9</category>
        
        <category>SLC4A11</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project Scientist in Vision Science</title>
        <description>&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Led 1 experimental and 1 in silico project investigating the molecular origin of photoreceptor discrete- and continuous-noise (2 firstauthor
manuscripts in final preparations).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Combined machine learning methods with electrophysiological recordings of single-photon responses to identify phosphodiesterase as
the driver for photon-detection limits in rod photoreceptors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentored and trained a small team of post doc and staff research personnel on custom acquisition hardware, analysis software, and
data analysis theory and methodology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/project.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/project.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ph.D. Molecular, Cellular, And Integrative Physiology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thesis Title:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mechanisms of detection sensitivity and adaptation in the rod visual pathway.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/phd.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/experiences/phd.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>experiences</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mechanisms of detection sensitivity and adaptation in the rod visual pathway</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://escholarship.org/uc/item/4tt400wt&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vision begins in the retina, where photoreceptors have the
task of discriminating incomingphotons from intrinsic cellular
noise. Vertebrates have evolved a duplex retina, in which rod and
cone photoreceptors respond over a broad range of light intensities
from single photons to bright light. Rods evolved from less
sensitive cone-like photoreceptors and are responsible for mediating
the lowest 8 orders of magnitude of light intensity. At the lowest
threshold of vision, rods detect single photons and transmit signals
to downstream neurons in a specialized circuit. In the rod visual
pathway, tens of rods converge onto a single rod bipolar cell, where
noise from the rods is filtered, and rod signals are processed for
further downstream transmission. It is unclear which evolutionary
changes imparted such sensitivity to rods, and how these advantages
allow for rods to discriminate single photons from intrinsic noise.
In downstream bipolar cells, the mechanism for setting the filtering
threshold is unknown. Further, it is unclear what implications of
the thresholding of rod bipolar cells have on vision in scotopic
light levels. In this thesis, I investigated the mechanisms that
work together to define the threshold of vision. To gain
understanding of the nature of vision at the absolute threshold, I
worked with three main goals in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 1: Determine the set of changes that make feasible 
the incredible sensitivity of rods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 2: Assess contributions of transduction proteins to the
detection of single photons versus intrinsic noise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Goal 3: Measure the ability of rod bipolar cells to shape and parse rod
signals over several orders of magnitude of ambient light levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve these goals, I collected single-cell electrophysiological
from mouse rods and rod bipolar cells. I analyzed the data with
statistical models to determine parameters that described the
mechanisms of visual threshold and adaptation. I also used
statistical modeling to help validate results of mathematical
modeling from our collaborators in the Reingruber Lab (Paris,
France), which show that the important differences between rods and
cones are reflected in the cone as a reduced outer segment volume, a
decreased amplification through the transduction cascade, a faster
turnover rate of the cyclic guanosine monophosphate second
messenger, and an accelerated rate of decay of the phosphodiesterase
(PDE) enzyme (goal 1). Through analysis of intrinsic noise in rods,
I showed that PDE is the critical transduction element both setting
the noise level and limiting the detection threshold and variability
for single-photon absorptions (goal 2). Further, measurements in rod
bipolar cells revealed that rod bipolar cells have a
calcium-dependent feedback mechanism that allows rod bipolar cells
to respond robustly to single-photon absorptions in the minority of
the rods, while continuing to signal in brighter backgrounds that
also cause rod adaptation (goal 3). Taken together, my work has
helped delineate the fundamental mechanisms of signal detection and
processing at the threshold of vision and over the dynamic range of
rod vision.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2022 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022b.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022b.html</guid>
        
        <category>visual neuroscience</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        <category>photon detection</category>
        
        <category>adaptation</category>
        
        <category>dynamical modeling</category>
        
        <category>software design</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Circadian and ultradian rhythms in normal mice and in a mouse model of Huntington&apos;s disease
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1080/07420528.2021.2014516&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Circadian rhythms in core body temperature (CBT) have been
widely studied, but fewer studies have explored higher-frequency
(ultradian) rhythms in detail. We analyzed CBT recordings from young
and middle-aged wild-type mice as well as from the Q175 model of
Huntington’s disease (HD), at sufficient temporal resolution to
address the question of ultradian rhythms. We used model selection
methods to show that the overall circadian pattern was better fit by
a square wave than a sine wave. Then, using Fourier analysis of the
CBT rhythms, we identified the spectral signature of an 8-hour
oscillation that occurs in the night but not the day, an observation
that can be confirmed by direct inspection of the rhythms. This
diurnal amplitude modulation of the 8-hour rhythm was lost with
aging as well as in the HD model. Thus, the impact of aging and
disease is seen here in the loss of the ability to separate rhythms
into a daytime phase and a nighttime phase. These findings raise the
possibility that ultradian rhythms in CBT may be a useful biomarker
for the pathology within the central nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 00:01:01 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022a.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/griffis2022a.html</guid>
        
        <category>circadian rhythms</category>
        
        <category>ultradian rhythms</category>
        
        <category>Fourier analysis</category>
        
        <category>biosignals analysis</category>
        
        <category>Huntington\&apos;s disease</category>
        
        <category>aging</category>
        
        <category>biomarker</category>
        
        <category>core body temperature</category>
        
        <category>physiological oscillations</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Energy shortage in human and mouse models of SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1167/iovs.61.8.39&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To elucidate the molecular events in solute carrier family 4 member 11 (SLC4A11)-deficient corneal endothelium that lead to the endothelial dysfunction that characterizes the dystrophies associated with SLC4A11 mutations, congenital hereditary endothelial dystrophy (CHED) and Fuchs endothelial corneal dystrophy 4. Comparative transcriptomic analysis (CTA) was performed in primary human corneal endothelial cells (pHCEnC) and murine corneal endothelial cells (MCEnC) with normal and reduced levels of SLC4A11 (SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC) and Slc4a11 (Slc4a11−/− MCEnC), respectively. Validation of differentially expressed genes was performed using immunofluorescence staining of CHED corneal endothelium, as well as western blot and quantitative PCR analysis of SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC and Slc4a11−/− MCEnC. Functional analyses were performed to investigate potential functional changes associated with the observed transcriptomic alterations. CTA revealed inhibition of cell metabolism and ion transport function as well as mitochondrial dysfunction, leading to reduced adenosine triphosphate (ATP) production, in SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC and Slc4a11−/− MCEnC. Co-localization of SNARE protein STX17 with mitochondria marker COX4 was observed in CHED corneal endothelium, as was activation of AMPK–p53/ULK1 in both SLC4A11 KD pHCEnC and Slc4a11−/− MCEnC, providing additional evidence of mitochondrial dysfunction and mitophagy. Reduced Na+-dependent HCO3− transport activity and altered NH4Cl-induced membrane potential changes were observed in Slc4a11−/− MCEnC. Reduced steady-state ATP levels and subsequent activation of the AMPK–p53 pathway provide a link between the metabolic functional deficit and transcriptome alterations, as well as evidence of insufficient ATP to maintain the Na+/K+-ATPase corneal endothelial pump as the cause of the edema that characterizes SLC4A11-associated corneal endothelial dystrophies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/zhang2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/zhang2020.html</guid>
        
        <category>CHED</category>
        
        <category>endothelial corneal dystrophy</category>
        
        <category>CRISPR-Cas9</category>
        
        <category>SLC4A11</category>
        
        <category>electrophysiology</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A kinetic analysis of mouse rod and cone photoreceptor responses</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://physoc.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1113/JP279524&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most vertebrates have rod and cone photoreceptors, which
differ in their sensitivity and response kinetics. We know that rods
evolved from cone-like precursors through the expression of
different transduction genes or the same genes at different levels,
but we do not know which molecular differences were most important.
We have approached this problem in mouse retina by analysing the
kinetic differences between rod flash responses and recent
voltage-clamp recordings of cone flash responses, using a model
incorporating the principal features of photoreceptor transduction.
We apply a novel method of analysis using the log-transform of the
current, and we ask which of the model’s dynamic parameters need be
changed to transform the flash response of a rod into that of a
cone. The most important changes are a decrease in the gain of the
response, reflecting a reduction in amplification of the
transduction cascade; an increase in the rate of turnover of cGMP in
darkness; and an increase in the rate of decay of activated
phosphodiesterase, with perhaps also an increase in the rate of
decay of light-activated visual pigment. Although we cannot exclude
other differences, and in particular alterations in the Ca2+ economy
of the photoreceptors, we believe that we have identified the
kinetic parameters principally responsible for the differences in
the flash responses of the two kinds of photoreceptors, which were
likely during evolution to have resulted in the duplex retina.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/reingruber2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/reingruber2020.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evidence of axon connectivity across a spinal cord transection in rats treated with epidural stimulation and motor training combined with olfactory ensheathing cell transplantation.
</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.expneurol.2018.07.015&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Olfactory ensheathing cells (OECs) are unique glia that
support axon outgrowth in the olfactory system, and when used as
cellular therapy after spinal cord injury, improve recovery and axon
regeneration. Here we assessed the effects of combining OEC
transplantation with another promising therapy, epidural electrical
stimulation during a rehabilitative motor task. Sprague-Dawley rats
received a mid-thoracic transection and transplantation of OECs or
fibroblasts (FBs) followed by lumbar stimulation while climbing an
inclined grid. We injected pseudorabies virus (PRV) into hindlimb
muscles 7-months post-injury to assess connectivity across the
transection. Analyses showed that the number of serotonergic (5-HT)
axons that crossed the rostral scar border and the area of
neurofilament-positive axons in the injury site were both greater in
OEC- than FB-treated rats. We detected PRV-labeled cells rostral to
the transection and remarkable evidence of 5-HT and PRV axons
crossing the injury site in 1 OEC- and 1 FB-treated rat. The axons
that crossed suggested either axon regeneration (OEC) or small areas
of probable tissue sparing (FB). Most PRV-labeled thoracic neurons
were detected in laminae VII or X, and ~25% expressed Chx10, a
marker for V2a interneurons. These findings suggest potential
regeneration or sparing of circuits that connect thoracic
interneurons to lumbar somatic motor neurons. Despite evidence of
axonal connectivity, no behavioral changes were detected in this
small-scale study. Together these data suggest that when
supplemented with epidural stimulation and climbing, OEC
transplantation can increase axonal growth across the injury site
and may promote recovery of propriospinal circuitry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 01:01:01 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/thornton2018.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://khrisgriffis.com/publications/thornton2018.html</guid>
        
        <category>spinal cord injury</category>
        
        <category>immunohistochemsitry</category>
        
        <category>olfactory glia</category>
        
        <category>neural repair</category>
        
        
        <category>publications</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
